<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jacques Dupuis</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Jacques Dupuis</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>(Who Isn&#39;t) On the Radio</title>
      <link>/who-isnt-on-the-radio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/who-isnt-on-the-radio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(November, 2024)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Before continuing, note that the following is based on data collected in 2019 and may not be an accurate picture of the current state of classical radio programming at these stations today in 2024. We are currently working on updating this project to reflect current/recent statistics, with intent to submit for publication.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This project began with a fairly straightforward question: How does programming on American classical radio break down along gender lines for composers heard over the airwaves?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aaron Copland&#39;s Lincoln Portrait in Cincinnati </title>
      <link>/posts/cincinnati-lincoln-portrait/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/posts/cincinnati-lincoln-portrait/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;28 July 2023&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As part of writing a program note for the Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra&amp;rsquo;s October 2023 performances of Aaron Copland&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Lincoln Portrait&lt;/em&gt; (1942) with narration by George Takei, I&amp;rsquo;ve been tracing performances in and around the city, especially with the CSO. The array of people who have declaimed the spoken portion of the piece is an important part of the piece&amp;rsquo;s longer and wider story, and Cincinnati&amp;rsquo;s performances give us a good idea of who has done this. In Cincinnati, some very prominent names show up (Maya Angelou, Neil Armstrong, Katherine Hepburn), but there is also a significant local presence–regional media personalities and politicians, as well as amateur performers, like those who presented for youth and high school concerts. The list gives us a sense of how bridges are built within local communities, and how music is one especially vital connector. Aside from the amateur performances, the American Bicentennial year of 1976 stands out to me with numerous performances, including one conducted by Copland.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Acousmetric Mrs. Davis</title>
      <link>/posts/mrs-davis-acousmetre/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/posts/mrs-davis-acousmetre/</guid>
      <description>&lt;table&gt;&#xA;  &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/mrs-davis/hilde.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Acousmatic Nunnery&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;  &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4 June 2023&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’ll get to &lt;em&gt;Mrs. Davis&lt;/em&gt;, I promise.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Much of my work centers on things in the more distant past, but lately I’ve been chipping away at a project on a trope that seems to me to be something of a canary-sized albatross in film-sound scholarship: Michel Chion’s &lt;em&gt;acousmetre&lt;/em&gt;. (For SEO purposes, I&amp;rsquo;m using the anglicized version of acousmêtre here.) Chion elaborated the concept of a disembodied voice in his 1982 book, &lt;a href=&#34;http://michelchion.com/books/4-la-voix-au-cinema&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;La Voix au cinéma&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (translated by Claudia Gorbman in 1999). Chion terms a (mostly filmic) being whose voice belongs to a body that may or may not be seen (visually apparent) in the course of the movie. Omnipresent, omniscient, omnipotent figures appeal to screenwriters for countless understandable reasons, and its availability and flexibility makes it just as interesting as an interpretive tool. It’s also an enduring type of narrative being, stretching back to the iconic the Wizard of Oz and Norbert Jacques’s grotesque &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3nbKy2Hp1AA&#34;&gt;Dr. Mabuse&lt;/a&gt; from Fritz Lang’s films (two of Chion’s exemplars &lt;em&gt;avant la lettre&lt;/em&gt;). These characters emblematize another (perhaps &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; other) important acousmêtric trait, the liquidation of special powers upon visual reveal. For Oz, the jig is up once Toto—bless him—goes behind the curtain.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Liza Met Clara</title>
      <link>/posts/schumann-lehmann/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/posts/schumann-lehmann/</guid>
      <description>&lt;table&gt;&#xA;  &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/schumann-lehmann/lehmann-eyes.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Liza Lehmann&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;  &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;17 July 2022&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the week since her 160th birthday, I’ve been thinking about and listening to the music of Liza Lehmann, whose renown depends heavily on which book you’re reading or who you ask and where you are. She was—as many remarked on her July 11th birthday—quite prolific, writing some 350 songs, a few stage pieces, and some instrumental music for piano or piano/violin.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;&#xA;      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/EsowexlzA3A?autoplay=0&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;end=0&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;mute=0&amp;amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lehman&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Cobweb Castle&lt;/em&gt;, a set of harmonically and melodically evocative character pieces—I would recommend hearing at least &amp;ldquo;Evensong&amp;rdquo; (starting at 11:18 above, performed by Erica Sipes), not to be confused with Lehmann&amp;rsquo;s famous song of that name.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CV</title>
      <link>/cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/cv/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You can download a PDF copy of my CV &lt;a href=&#34;/cv/jacques-dupuis-cv.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Current from spring 2025.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Abagnales Sing Along</title>
      <link>/posts/catch-me-diegesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/posts/catch-me-diegesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;table&gt;&#xA;  &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/catch-me-diegesis/anybody_kelly.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Still from Has Anybody Here Seen Kelly&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;  &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;7 January 2022&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Catch Me If You Can&lt;/em&gt; (2002), as a piece of filmmaking, is sort of famously clever, sometimes to an extreme, even saccharine degree that tests our willingness to buy into its premise. Its music and sound play a pretty significant role in that challenge; the somewhat uncharacteristic but enthralling style John Williams composed in for the score draws us in, and the various uses of pre-existing music throughout the film do the work that kind of music usually does in film. Maybe the most famous clever moment of pre-existing music is the emotionally fraught use of Nat King Cole&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Christmas Song&amp;rdquo; in the movie’s denouement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Women Vienna Honored</title>
      <link>/posts/clara-gesellschaft/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/posts/clara-gesellschaft/</guid>
      <description>&lt;table&gt;&#xA;  &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/gsdmembers/gesellschaft-image.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;  &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.europeana.eu/en/item/15514/KI_23246_6_3&#34;&gt;via Europeana&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;28 November 2021&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The project I’m currently finishing an initial draft of is an essay for an upcoming edited collection on the Schumanns, and my contribution covers Clara’s honors and professional affiliations, coming out in the next couple years. I’ve been over-researching it a bit, because it’s led me down some interesting alleys and, as the editors said, these sorts of recognitions have little scholarly coverage. Not none, it’s just scattered and supports other studies, and there’s no dedicated study that I’ve found. One of those alleys has entailed trying to suss out what, for instance, honorary memberships signified, what they did for artist and institution, and who got them. Here are a couple of observations about that last issue.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a musicologist and (mostly amateur) musician currently living in Fort Wayne, Indiana. I am a clinical assistant professor of music theory and musicology at the Purdue University Fort Wayne School of Music.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I graduated from the University of Notre Dame in 2011 and earned my PhD in musicology from Brandeis University in 2021 with a dissertation on composers&amp;rsquo; importations of popular theater genres into—to borrow from historian, William Weber—high-prestige music making. My research focuses on music, history and aesthetics in German-speaking lands and the United States after 1800. I&amp;rsquo;m especially interested in ways that cultural hierarchies interact in, and across, various repertoires. Lately, I&amp;rsquo;ve turned my attention toward the voice and vocality in film and theater (musical or spoken). Among other topics, I have researched and written on:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
